# 大家好 去年兄弟抓了我兩隻香豬哦
Hi everyone! My buddy caught two of my pigs last year.
# 他現在 到現在也不給錢
But now… I mean he has never paid me, not even now.
# 今天我去他那裡抓了兩條白豬回來
So I caught two white pigs from his place today.
# 他說用那個香豬哏白豬配在一起生出來的哦
He said that it was bred from a Huanjiang pig and a white pig, you know.
# 看上去就很漂亮
They look really pretty.
# 兩條小白豬
Two white piggies
# 抬上去和那個黑豬一起餵
Let's carry them up there and keep them with that black pig,
# 看一下怎麼樣
and see what will happen.
# 誒 你們自由啦
Ey! You’re free now.
# 這個是 這公的
This one is, this is male.
# 你看 這小豬自己跑出來啦
Look! This piggy is coming out itself.
# 自己會跑出來哦
It comes out itself.
# 你看 兩條大白豬
Look! Two fat white pigs.
# 屁股上都黑色的
Their butts are black,
# 長了有胎記
with birthmarks.
# 它們在交流
They’re communicating.
# 你看 那小豬還想喝奶
Look! That piggy wants milk.
# 它那麼小就被我抓回來啦
I’ve caught them back here, though they’re still so small.
# 這沒事啊 看它都斷奶啦
No worries. They’ve already weaned, I bet
# 這個豬最 最大的話能長六七百斤的哦
These pigs can reach up to, up to three hundred and fifty kilograms, you know.
# 它養個一兩年的話可以長到很大的
They can be super huge in a year or two.
# 過年的时候應該有兩百斤
I think they could reach around a hundred kilograms by the Chinese New Year.
# 一人一百斤
Let’s have fifty kilograms each.
# 要不要一人一條
Or you want one each?
# 你看 耆們慢慢就會 慢慢就會熟悉的
Look! They’ll be gradually, gradually familiar with this place.
# 它們自己
They’ll have,
# 自己玩自己的
they'll have their own fun.
# 它們自己會自己吃啦
They’ll find their own food.
# 不用我們管啦
We don’t really need to take care of them.
# 不管它們 讓它們自己在 在這裡玩
Leave them alone and let them have, have fun here.
# 啊 你們在這裡玩就好了啊
Ah! Stay here and have fun! Everything will be fine.
# 不是抓你們 不要那麼怕
Don’t be so scared. I’m not catching you.
# 小豬已經安頓好啦 我去看一下兄弟家的臍橙
The piggies have already been settled down. Let’s have a look at my buddy’s navel oranges.
# 今年的臍橙聽說產量很高
I’ve heard that the yield is really high this year.
# 就在那裡村口 就我們村的
It’s right at the entrance of the village, our village.
# 有點黃出來啦 看見沒有
Look! It’s turning yellow, see?
# 慢慢地黃起來啦
It’s turning yellow gradually.
# 你看 三胞胎
Look! Triplet
# 一樹都是 你看這棵
They’re all over the tree. Have a look at this tree!
# 好多啊今年 碩果累纍纍
There are a lot this year. So fruitful!
# 今年產量好高哦
The yield this year is really high,
# 比去年高很多誒
much higher than last year.
# 你看 這些都是種了差多快五年的樹啦
Look! These are about five-year old trees.
# 五年才那麼大一點 那麼大一點的幹子
Five years, but it's still not really big, the branches are still not really that big.
# 你看這個樹都斷啦 太多啦
Look! This branch is about to break. There are just too many oranges.
# 直接掰下來啦
Let me just pick one right away.
# 看一下有沒有掉在地上的
See if any has dropped onto the ground.
# 哎呀 真的有個掉在地上的
Aya! Here's really one on the ground.
# 你看是不是 泥巴都有啦
This one, isn’t it? I can even see mud on it.
# 嘗一下 看下怎麼樣 味道
Let me have a try, and see how it is, how it tastes.
# 現在應該可以好吃啦
It might be tasty, by this time.
# 嗯 還有點酸
Um! It’s still a little bit sour.
# 黃一些就好吃啦 現在還不是很黃
It will taste much better when it turns yellow. But it’s still a bit green.
# 現在還不是很甜 太酸啦
It’s not really that sweet, too sour.
# 臍橙都還沒熟 看下路過 路過兄弟家這個紅薯
The navel oranges are not yet ripe. We now pass by my, my buddy’s sweet potatoes.
# 搞點回去
Let’s get some back home.
# 這個紅薯 不知道有沒有
These are sweet potatoes. But I don’t know if there are really any,
# 挖了才知道
at least not before I start digging.
# 哎呀 你看
Aya! Look!
# 你看 這裡有一個了吧 是不是
Look! Here’s one, right?
# 那麼小 那麼小也可以吃的啦
It’s so small. It’s small but it’s also edible.
# 是不是
Right?
# 這樣紅薯很漂亮的哦 看下 不大又不小
This kind of sweet potatoes are really pretty. Look! They're not too big, not too small.
# 剛剛好
Perfect size.
# 這還有幾個啊
Here are a few more.
# 這個小太了 這個拿回去給小豬吃
This one is too small. I’ll take it back for the piggies.
# 誒呀 這麼大啊
Eya! So big.
# 這個才大 這個
This is huge, this one.
# 夠啦夠啦 不要啦
Enough, enough! No more
# 看一下 看一下子就挖到那麼多
Look! I have, I have so many here in just a few minutes.
# 剛好 這裡有一個袋子
It just so happens that, here is a bag.
# 肯定兄弟給我準備的
It must be prepared by my buddy, specially for me.
# 好啦 把這紅薯藤帶回去給豬吃
Alright! Let me take these leaves for the pigs.
# 把這紅薯 把它洗一下
The sweet potatoes… Let me wash them.
# 你看
Look!
# 這小紅薯
These small sweet potatoes.
# 挖番薯的同時順手帶了幾個玉米回來 (註︰不知怎樣表達這個「順手」，我想意思就是在附近，「來都來了」)
Offhand, I’ve taken a couple of corns back as well.
# 這樣剝乾淨點用那個
Peel them well, and then, you know,
# 鍚紙裹起來就直接這樣 烤熟它就可以啦
wrap them up with aluminium foil, and then we can, just grill them right away.
# 這樣就漂亮啦
It’s really pretty now.
# 嗯 可以啦 準備 上炭
Um! Alright! Everything’s ready! Get the charcoal!
# 先把這裡兩放到這裡先
Let me first put these two here.
# 你看 這樣就熟的 熟的快啦
Look! Then, it’s gonna take, take less time.
# 再過鄰個小時候可以開吃啦
We can start after half an hour.
# 這個玉米
The corns,
# 熟了哦
are done now.
# 應該熟了 按道理來說的話
They should be done now, theoretically.
# 哎呀 好燙啊
Aya! It’s really hot!
# 金黃的身體
Golden yellow body.
# 泡點水 好燙啊
It’s too hot. Let me rinse it.
# 好啦 嘗一下
Alright! Let me try,
# 嘗一下味道怎樣
and see how it tastes.
# 嗯
Um!
# 好香
It smells so good,
# 真的好香啊 好好吃啊
really, really good! It’s so tasty!
# 看下這紅薯
Have a look at the sweet potatoes.
# 這才是紅色
This is what a "red potato" should look like.
(In Chinese, sweet potato is called "Red Potato")
# 你看 這個好啊 這個小 小紅薯
Look! It's really tasty, this small, small sweet potatoes.
# 都熟透了 它只是這個水分被蒸乾了一樣
It’s done now, in fact. It’s just dried out.
# 嗯 好吃啊 搞一個
Um! Tasty! Have one!
# 剛好又紅又紛的
It’s red and mushy, prefect!
# 今天視頻到這裡啦 準備吃晚飯啦
The video ends here. We need to get ready for dinner.